Sebastián

Bustamante Jaramillo

Curriculum Vitae



I am a physicist with a strong interest in astrophysics, specifically in cosmology. I have always thought humanity's understanding the large-scale universe through science is like a bacteria colony trying to build a complete map of the earth or even more. I am looking forward to cooperate and get involve with high quality research teams in order to contribute my humble grain of sand to this grand and exciting enterprise called science. If I were asked to introduce myself in four words, they would be astrophysics-programming-swimming-guitar.

GENERAL INFORMATION

lame Sebastián Bustamante Jaramillo.

Date of Birth 20th June, 1990.

Place of Birth Maceo - Colombia.

Nationality Colombian.

Marital Status Single.

 $\textbf{Identification} \quad \text{c.c.} \ 1128400433 \ .$

Address Avenida 21 # 57 AA 65, Bello - Colombia.

 $\begin{array}{lll} \textbf{Home tel.} & +057 \; (4) \; 4820138 \; . \\ & \textbf{Mobile} & +057 \; 3108992409 \; . \\ & \textbf{e-mail} & \text{macsebas} 33@\text{gmail.com}. \end{array}$

Inst. e-mail sbustama@pegasus.udea.edu.co.

EDUCATION

2001-2006 High School Diploma, Institución Educativa Cisneros, Cisneros, Colombia.

2007-2012 B.Sc. in Physics, Institute of Physics, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Thesis "The place of the Milky Way and Andromeda in the cosmic web".

Description This study is aimed to characterize the local environment of Local Group (LG)-like systems from dark matter simulations of the large-scale universe. Using two different types of simulations, an unconstrained simulation (Bolshoi project) and a set of constrained simulations (CLUES project), it is first constructed a LG-like sample based upon observational constrains on the kinematic properties and isolation criteria of the real LG, along with the results of the CLUES simulations. By using a tensorial scheme based upon the peculiar velocity field of the dark matter, the V-web scheme, it is classified the local environment of systems in each simulation. Finally, it has been found that

is classified the local environment of systems in each simulation. Finally, it has been found that LG-like systems lies preferentially in sheet-like regions, furthermore a significant environmental bias for the total mass and the specific energy. No correlations have been found for the specific angular momentum and other studied properties.

Advisor Jaime E. Forero-Romero, Ph.D.

Additional Education

2008 Extension Course of Planetary Sciences, Faculty of Exact and Natural Sciences, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

FIELDS OF INTEREST

Cosmology. Large-scale structure formation. Galaxy astrophysics. Planetary interior. Numerical simulations. Computational astrophysics. General astrophysics and physics. Programming.

LANGUAGES

Spanish Native speaker.

English Good.

Computer Skills

Systems Linux, MSWindows ME/XP/Vista/7/8.

Development C/C++, Python, Basic, TI Basic, shell scripts.

Software Mathematica, LaTeX, gnuplot, Gadget.

Simulation N-body simulations, SPH, MonteCarlo, Finite Differences, Numerical integrators, Audio processing.

Tools

Repositories A list of my projects can be found in my github page: https://github.com/sbustamante.

HONOURS, AWARDS, AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

2001-2006 High School Diploma, Institución Educativa Cisneros, Cisneros, Colombia.

TEACHING

Assistant Physics 1 (Mechanics), 2013/1, Faculty of Exact and Natural Sciences, Universidad de Antioquia,

Instructor Medellín, Colombia.

Assistant Computational Complement of Physics 2 (Electricity and Magnetism), 2013/1, Faculty of

Instructor Exact and Natural Sciences, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Assistant Computational Complement of Physics 3 (Oscillations and Waves), 2013/1, Faculty of Exact

Instructor and Natural Sciences, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Adjunct Introductory Physics, 2013/2, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colom-

Professor bia

Adjunct Laboratory of Physics 1 (Mechanics), 2013/2, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad de Antioquia,

Professor Medellín, Colombia.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2010-2011 Young Investigator Programme, Fundamental of quantum mechanics, *Group of Atomic and Molecular Physics (GFAM), Committee for Research Development (CODI), Universidad de Antioquia*, Medellín, Colombia.

2011-2012 Young Investigator Programme, Thermal evolution of rocky exoplanets, *Group of Computational Physics and Astrophysics (FACom), Committee for Research Development (CODI), Universidad de Antioquia*, Medellín, Colombia.

August, 2012 Research Internship, Physics Department, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia.

Conferences, schools and workshops attended

- 2012 Regional WCRP/SPARC Workshop with focus on the Southern Hemisphere and South America., Universidad de Buenos Aires, November 26-27, Buenos Aires, Argentina.
- Poster: Moisture Flux across Northerm of South America using ERA Interim data.
 - 2012 **XI Meeting of teaching in science and mathematics.**, Universidad de Antioquia, Universidad EAFIT, April 19-20, Medellín, Colombia.
 - 2011 **XI Colombian Congress of Meteorology.**, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, sede Bogotá, March 23-25, Bogotá, Colombia.
 - 2008 **I Colombian Congress of Astronomy and Astrophysics.**, Universidad de Antioquia, Universidad EAFIT, August 19-20, Medellín, Colombia.

Miscellaneous

Computer C, Linux, Mathematica, CDO, GrADS .

Skills

Languages Spanish (native), English.

References

• Jaime E. Forero-Romero (Advisor)

Professor and Researcher, Foundations and Teaching Group of Physics and Dynamical Systems, Atomic and Molecular Physics Group.

Instituto de Física, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Phone: 57-4-219 64 39.

banghelo@fisica.udea.edu.co